Finding aid for the Old Lesbians Organizing for Change records SSC.MS.00671
Sophia Smith Collection
Old Lesbians Organizing for Change records
1986-2018
Sophia Smith Collection
Old Lesbians Organizing for Change
SSC.MS.00671
27.5 linear feet (30 containers)
13 Gigabytes
Old Lesbians Organizing for Change(OLOC) is a national (United States) organization of lesbian activists age 60 and over. This collection includes extensive documentation of all OLOC gatherings since 1987, including photographs of activities, and videotapes of panel discussions and keynote speeches. Administrative files, newsletters and other publications, and educational and public relations materials are also included, as is a history of the organization. The collection also contains a small amount of materials related to Shevy Healy, a longtime activist and one of OLOC's founders.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Old Lesbians Organizing for Change started donating its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2011 and has made regular transfers of additional records since then. Materials were donated by Susan Wiseheart, Alix Dobkin, and Margie Reed, members of OLOC. As of 2018, the collection includes seven distinct accessions.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series.
Series:
Administrative Files
Gatherings
Shevy Healy papers
Biographical / Historical
In 2018, more than 30 years after its founding, Old Lesbians Organizing for Change (OLOC), a national (U.S.) organization for lesbians 60 and over, defines its mission as "addressing what it means to be Old and to be Lesbian; finding ways to gather groups of Old Lesbians together for ongoing support; working against all oppressions that affect Old Lesbians; [and] standing in solidarity with allies for racial, economic and social justice."
The book Look Me in the Eye: Old Women, Aging and Ageism by Barbara Macdonald and Cynthia Rich (1983), which exposed harsh realities of ageism on old women, was the inspiration for the founding of Old Lesbians Organizing for Change. In April 1987, the First West Coast Conference by and for old lesbians in Southern California was held at the California State University Dominguez Campus in Carson, California. It was so successful that in August 1989, old lesbians in Northern California sponsored The Second West Coast Conference. Out of the larger group of old lesbians attending these two events came a smaller group of sixteen that wished to concentrate their efforts on challenging ageism. This group founded The Old Lesbian Organizing Committee, which was later renamed Old Lesbians Organizing for Change.
Participation was strictly limited to lesbians sixty years of age and older, although OLOC has always welcomed the support of younger lesbians, encouraging them to work against ageism while respecting the need for separate space for Old Lesbians. To minimize travel expenses for committee members, most meetings during the first two years were held in California. A concerted effort was then made to expand the geographic representation by moving the meetings around the country.
OLOC quickly established a newsletter to reach Old Lesbians around the country and began enrolling subscribers. Committee members focused early efforts on development of educational materials on ageism, using the familiar and effective format of consciousness raising sessions. These materials were pooled and published in The Facilitator's Handbook: Confronting Ageism: Consciousness Raising for Lesbians 60 and Over (early 1990s).
Much of OLOC's early work was done within both the women's and LGBT communities, since ageism was as entrenched in those communities as it was in society at large. Often at its own expense, OLOC provided speakers and presentations to dozens of workshops and conferences, challenging the status quo and demanding to be a part of the process. OLOC felt strongly that younger people couldn't effectively speak for Old Lesbians and insisted that Old Lesbians be allowed to represent themselves. OLOC was a strong and highly visible part of the National Lesbian Conference in Atlanta in 1991 as well as the March on Washington in 1993. By 1992, OLOC sought and gained non-profit status, incorporating in the state of Texas, and in 1994 also achieved tax-exempt status.
In addition to publishing a quarterly newsletter, The OLOC Reporter, and holding biennial Gatherings, OLOC confronts ageism wherever it is found. OLOC has also been associated with the Old Lesbian Oral Herstory Project, which gathers the unique stories of lesbians who are seventy years of age and older. OLOC operates both as a national organization and through local chapters that have formed across the country.
[source: OLOC Website]
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
This collection contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
Related Materials
See also the Old Lesbians Oral History Project
Scope and Contents
The Old Lesbians Organizing for Change records contain extensive documentation of all OLOC events and gatherings since 1987, including photographs of events and videotapes of panel discussions and keynote speeches. Administrative files, newsletters and other publications, and educational and public relations materials are also included, as is a history of the organization. The collection also contains the professional files of Shevy Healy, a longtime activist and one of OLOC's founders.
Included are materials regarding the founding and development or the group's oral herstroy project. The project originated with Arden Eversmeyer after a member of the Houston group she founded in 1987, Old Lesbians Over Age Fifty (LOAF) passed away in 1990 and she realized her stories would be lost.
The collection also contains materials related to OLOC's birthday card project which originated out of the founding mothers' irritation about the ageism in commercial birthday cards. OLOC developed birthday card workshops and eventually produced its own line of birthday cards.
Separated Materials
In 2019, duplicate AV materials and unrelated memorabilia was removed.
Ageism -- United States; Lesbian communities--United States--History--Sources; Lesbians -- United States -- History; Lesbians activists -- United States -- Sources; Older lesbians -- United States; Older people -- United States; Older women -- United States -- Sources; Audiotapes; DVD video discs; Electronic mail; Electronic records; Grant proposals; Manuals; Publications; Videotapes; Computer media; Fund raising; Financial records; Photographs.; memorabilia; Notes; correspondence; Newsletters; Old Lesbians Organizing for Change; Wiseheart, Susan; Dobkin, Alix; Reed, Margie; Wiseheart, Susan; Wiseheart, Susan; Dobkin, Alix; Reed, Margie
- Administrative files, 1987-2018; 1
  Arrangement
  The series has been left in its original order.
  Subseries:
  Chronological files
  Alphabetical files
  Financial records
  Newsletters
  Publications
  Steering Committee records
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains administrative records of OLOC, including newsletters, financial records, correspondence, Steering Committee materials, publicity, photographs, and AV materials.
  - Chronological files, 1989-2010; A
    - Founding documents including mailing lists, correspondence, photos, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: Old Lesbian Conference II San Francisco video recording, 1989; 3 items (3 VHS tapes) (Box 21)
    - Founding documents: Old Lesbian Conference and Mother Tongue Theater Collective video recording, 1989; 5 items (5 DVDs) (Box 28, Box 29)
    - Founding documents: 1st Meeting San Diego video recording, 1989; 9 items (2 VHS tapes and 7 DVDs) (Box 21, Box 28, Box 29)
    - Founding documents: 2nd Meeting Santa Barbara video recording, 1990; 5 items (5 VHS tapes) (Box 21)
    - Founding documents: 3rd Meeting Albuquerque video recording, 1990; 6 items (6 VHS tapes) (Box 22)
    - Founding documents: 4th Meeting Walnut Creek video recording, 1990; 5 items (5 VHS tapes) (Box 22)
    - Founding documents: OLOC Fundraiser LA video recording, 1991; 2 items (2 VHS tapes) (Box 23)
    - Founding documents: 7th Meeting Long Beach video recording, 1991; 8 items (8 VHS tapes) (Box 23, Box 24)
    - Founding documents: Visualization for CR on Finances audio recording, 1991; 1 items (1 audio cassette) (Box 28)
    - Founding documents: contacts, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: correspondence and mailing lists, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: membership lists and presentation slides, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: miscellaneous materials from 7th meeting, 1991 October (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: miscellaneous materials from 2nd meeting, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: mailing lists and correspondence, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: release forms and invoices (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: meeting handouts, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: lists, including of lesbian spaces and mailing lists, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: mailing lists, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: early mailing lists, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: Old Lesbian Organization Committee conference documents, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: correspondence, meeting minutes and other notes, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: correspondence, receipts and miscellaneous notes, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: planning materials for National Lesbian Conference, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: outreach letter and completed response forms for Southern California meeting, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: presentation slides (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: regional correspondence, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: press releases, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: photographs (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: orientation packet, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: newsletter criteria, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: Atlanta photographs (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: photographs, 1991 October (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: mailing lists, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: job description, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: incorporation papers, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: funding raising materials, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: first brochure (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: financial reports, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: correspondence, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: "contact person", 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: budget (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: clippings, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: photographs, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: press releases, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: newsletter articles (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: mailings and lists, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: grant video recording, 1990; 3 items (3 DVD) (Box 28, Box 29)
    - Founding documents: correspondence, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: newsletter articles, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: Second West Coast Conference, 1989 August 6 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: organizational notes, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: correspondence, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: recording of first OLOC meeting, San Diego, 1989; 3 items (3 DVDs) (Box 1)
    - Founding documents: financial records including receipts, contributions and workshop informtion, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Founding documents: Dialogue on the Word Old at Mazen Collection video recordings, 1991; 8 items (3 VHS tapes and 5 DVDs) (Box 23, Box 28, Box 29)
    - Founding documents: Banner from West Coast Old Lesbian Conference, 1987 (Roll 30)
    - Founding documents: T-shirt from West Coast Old Lesbian Conference, 1 items (Box 20)
    - Social relations ageism workshop materials, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Sexuality-sensuality workshop materials, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Facilitators' Handbook - Confronting Ageism, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Fundraising material (Box 2)
    - Regional correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Ann Ramsey (Box 2)
    - Newsletter correspondence, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Materials related to the March on Washington, 1993 (Box 2)
    - OLOC papers of incorporation, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Newsletter articles, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Southwest region materials, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - Regional correspondence, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Photographs, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Mailing lists, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Orientation packet, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Newsletter collective materials, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Mailing lists, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Incorporation, 1992 (Box 2)
    - GLOE, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Group norms, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Fundraising, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Financial reports, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - Database lists, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Birthday card workshop (Box 2)
    - Articles, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Membership and supporters, 1992-1994 (Box 2)
    - Contact people and membership lists, 1992-1996 (Box 2)
    - Poster and Flag from March on Washington, 1993 (Box 20)
    - Articles, 1992-1994 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 2)
    - OLOC Old Lesbian Leadership Learning Seminar, October 1994 (Box 2)
    - Newsletter correspondence, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Photographs, April 1994 (Box 2)
    - Poster contest and expense report, 1994-1996 (Box 3)
    - Gay Games, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Holiday letter, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Leadership learning seminar, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Leadership seminar applications and evaluations, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Minutes: Annual Meeting of Directors, April 21, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Articles for "Reporter", 1994 (Box 3)
    - Membership lists, 1994 (Box 3)
    - New OLOC office, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Pat Bond Memorial Old Dyke Award, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Pattern for banner (Box 3)
    - Pictures, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Press release, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Regional correspondence, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Regional meeting fliers, 1994 (Box 3)
    - State contributions, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Texas Lesbian Conference, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Holiday fundraising letter, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Lesbian's Consciousness Raising, 1994; 3 items (3 audio cassettes) (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous newsletter and other articles, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - General correspondence, 1994-1996 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence: Mickey Spencer, 1994-1996 (Box 3)
    - Flag from Stonewall's 25th Anniversary, 1994 (Box 20)
    - Financial reports, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Fliers and other materials for First International Gathering by and for OLD Lesbians, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Fundraising literature, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Steering committee and gathering planning documents, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
    - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force workshop and other materials, 1994-1996 (Box 3)
    - Newsletter correspondence, 1994-1996 (Box 3)
    - OLOC database lists, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Photographs, 1995 (Box 3)
    - OLOC Provincetown materials, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Regional policy statement and related correspondence, 1995 (Box 3)
    - State contributions, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Steering committee membership requirements and lists, 1995 (Box 4)
    - White House conference, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
    - Newsletter and other articles, 1996 (Box 4)
    - American Society on Aging meeting materials, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Birthday card workshop materials (Box 4)
    - California corporation documents, 1996 (Box 4)
    - R. Silver Chanukah celebration materials including audio cassette, 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Photographs, 1996-04 (Box 4)
    - Sharon Jackson dissertation on lives of older lesbians with OLOC correspondence, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Financial reports and fund raising documents, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Gathering documents including banquet and publicity, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Newsletter correspondence, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Photographs of taping facilitators' book, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Steering committee list and procedures, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Annual meeting, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Financial documents including budget, fundraiser and contributions, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Steering committee, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, article, Del Martin and Phyllis Lyon, 1997-02-03 (Box 4)
    - Contributions and fundraising documents, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Photographs, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    - Steering committee member lists and invitations, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Newsletter and other articles, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Fundraiser materials, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Steering committee list and invitations, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Senoir Action in a Gay Environment (SAGE) conference brochures, 1999; Water damaged (Box 5)
    - Photographs, 2000-04 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 5)
    - Financial documents including fundraiser, possible funding sources and deposit records, 2000 (Box 5)
    - GLBT Historical mailer, 2000; water damage (Box 5)
    - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force miscellaneous materials, 2000 (Box 5)
    - Oral herstory project notice, 2000 (Box 5)
    - P.A. Coleman letter of resignation from steering committee, 2000 (Box 5)
    - OLOC Anniversary Invitation, 2000 (Box 20)
    - Publications and other articles, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Steering committee reservations documents, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Denver, Minneapolis and Portland OLOC documents, 2001 (Box 5)
    - E-mail address list, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Jan Griesinger materials, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Tracy Gary materials, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Pat Rutherford materials, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Annual meeting, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Newsletter and other articles, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Budget, fundraising, bank deposits, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Postal service records, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Toni Langfield material, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Polly Taylor materials, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Tobi's tirade, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Aritcles, 2003-2004 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 2003 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous financial documents, 2003 (Box 5)
    - Nancy Nystrom letter, 2003 (Box 5)
    - Old Lesbian Herstory Project (OHP) reports, 2003-2004 (Box 5)
    - Photographs, 2003-04 (Box 5)
    - Breed and Duplaix steering committee resignation letter, 2003 (Box 5)
    - Venue selection documents, 2003 (Box 5)
    - Technology materials including Web site and data transfer, 2003 (Box 5)
    - Fidelity Investment documents, 2004 (Box 5)
    - Attorney documents, 2004 (Box 5)
    - Grant and fundraising materials, 2004 (Box 5)
    - Dotty Fowler e-mail, 2004 (Box 5)
    - Letter to local groups, 2004 (Box 5)
    - Database information, 2004 (Box 5)
    - "Order Leaps Out of Chaos" gathering guide, 2003 (Box 6)
    - Policies and procedures, 2003 (Box 6)
    - Grants and fundraiser documents, 2004-2005 (Box 6)
    - Annual meeting with minutes, 2005 (Box 6)
    - OLOC brochure, 2005 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous photographs, 2005-2015 (Box 6)
    - Financial report, 2006 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Durham Gathering documents with audio, 2006; 3 items (3 DVDs) (Box 6)
    - Annual meetings with minutes, 2006 (Box 6)
    - Spring fundraiser, 2006 (Box 6)
    - Cover letter for Otter for OLOC history, 2007 (Box 6)
    - DC regional event documents, 2007 (Box 6)
    - Hudson Valley OLOC, 2007 (Box 6)
    - Field organizing materials, 2007 (Box 6)
    - Letterhead, 2007 (Box 6)
    - Long Beach Gay Pride materials with AV, 2007; 1 items (1 Mini DVD) (Box 6)
    - Policies and procedures manual, 2006-2007 (Box 6)
    - Travel directory, 2007 (Box 6)
    - Vancouver conference materials, 2007 (Box 6)
    - Long Beach Gay Pride Parade video recording, 2007; 1 items (1 DVD) (Box 28)
    - Travel directories, 2008 (Box 6)
    - OLOC miscellaneous materials, 2008 (Box 6)
    - History of OLOC report with drafts, 2007 (Box 6)
    - Steering committee material, 2008 (Box 6)
    - OLOC archive materials, 2008 (Box 6)
    - Duplicates of scanned materials, 2008 (Box 6)
    - JeffCo Dems GLBT Caucus Lapel Pins, 2008 (Box 20)
    - General Gathering documents including admission packets,brochure, check-in lists and miscellaneous, 2008 (Box 6)
    - General administrative files, 2008-2017; 4 items (4 DVDs) (Box 6)
    - Proclamation from the City of Oakland Celebrating the 25th Anniversary, 2014 (Box 20)
    - OLOC Banner (Box 20)
    - OLOC T-Shirts, 3 items (3 shirts) (Box 20)
  - Alphabetical files, 1987-2008; B
    - Articles, 1995-2000; undated (Box 6)
    - A Movement of Old Lesbians, 1995; undated (Box 6)
    - Ageism poster, undated (Box 6)
    - Ageism and the politics of beauty, 1988-1999 (Box 6)
    - Ageism handouts, 1991-1995; undated (Box 6)
    - Consciousness raising on ageism, 1987-1998; undated (Box 6)
    - Ageism/Consciousness raising materials, 1990-1991; undated (Box 6)
    - Aging articles, 1989-1995; undated (Box 6)
    - Articles of incorporation, 1992-1997 (Box 7)
    - Bios for memorial, undated (Box 7)
    - Steering Committee birthday cards, 2005-2007 (Box 7)
    - Birthday card project, 1995-1998; undated (Box 7)
    - Bay Area OLOC, 1997-2005 (Box 7)
    - Bookkeeper, 2001; undated (Box 7)
    - OLOC brochure, undated (Box 7)
    - Building local OLOC organizations, undated (Box 7)
    - Bulk mail, 1993; undated (Box 7)
    - Bulk mail receipts, 1992-2003 (Box 7)
    - California organizing packet, undated (Box 7)
    - Colorado OLOC, 1994-1996; undated (Box 7)
    - Conference calls, undated (Box 7)
    - Consciousness raising, undated (Box 7)
    - Contribution letter, undated (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 7)
    - Creating Change: speeches, 1997 (Box 7)
    - Diversity with a Difference, undated (Box 7)
    - Duties of state contact, undated (Box 7)
    - Email network, 1996 (Box 7)
    - Employment taxes, 1995 (Box 7)
    - Environmental Illness (EI), 1994 (Box 7)
    - Facilitating OLOC meetings, undated (Box 7)
    - Financial forms/documents, 1991-1994 (Box 7)
    - Ageism fishbowl, 1996 (Box 7)
    - Franchise tax exemption, 1994 (Box 7)
    - Fund development, undated (Box 7)
    - Fundraising notes/ideas, 1995-2007 (Box 7)
    - Greeting card ideas, undated (Box 7)
    - Group norms, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Handbook correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 7)
    - Handbook correspondence, 1990-1992; undated (Box 7)
    - Handbook notes, undated (Box 7)
    - Handbook notes/correspondence, 1991 (Box 7)
    - Taped handbook handouts, undated (Box 7)
    - Handbook revisions, 1993 (Box 7)
    - Grant proposal, 1992-1994 (Box 7)
    - Homophobia handouts, undated (Box 7)
    - In kind donations, 1993-1995; undated (Box 7)
    - Interns, 2000 (Box 7)
    - Bonnie Kell, 2000-2001 (Box 7)
    - Kim Klein workshop, 2001 (Box 7)
    - Packet for local groups, 2003 (Box 7)
    - Logo submissions, undated (Box 7)
    - Macdonald speech, undated (Box 7)
    - Mailing list: Organizations, undated (Box 7)
    - Del Martin, 2008 (Box 7)
    - Vera Martin, 1996-1998 (Box 7)
    - Membership/supporter letters, undated (Box 7)
    - Memorial fund, 1996 (Box 7)
    - Mentors, undated (Box 7)
    - Mission-goals-strategies, undated (Box 7)
    - Planning Committee: National Gathering for and by Old Lesbians, January 1-5, 1995 (Box 7)
    - Newsletter content, 1994 (Box 7)
    - Newsletter costs, 1994-1995 (Box 7)
    - Newsletter schedule, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Newsletter style sheets, 1993 (Box 7)